<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Health | F. Leblanc</title>
    <link>/category/health/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Health</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hufe976c661fb6135bd1164f77aadbc1d5_99438_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Health</title>
      <link>/category/health/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking saturated fats</title>
      <link>/post/rethinking-saturated-fats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/rethinking-saturated-fats/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A paper that will most likely raise a lot of controversies was published in JACC
beginning of august 2020, one of the top scientific journals in cardiology. The
article goes through a lot more then I cover here, but I wanted to make
accessible one of the main reasons why saturated fats have
been &lt;em&gt;erroneously&lt;/em&gt; demonized (if LDL and cholesterol are all clear for you
here’s my main point: &lt;ins&gt;Under the presumption that either LDLc or all LDLp were
important contributors to atherosclerosis, a diet that showed an increase in
either of these was (and still is by most) considered dangerous and to be
avoided.&lt;/ins&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-whats-ldl&#34;&gt;So what’s LDL?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LDL refers to low-density lipoprotein. This term is often confounded with
cholesterol as a molecule. Let’s first describe how these 2 terms differ.





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-cholesterol-molecule&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/88603daca664e9fcc51d9571d0d7659a.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;cholesterol molecule&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/88603daca664e9fcc51d9571d0d7659a.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    cholesterol molecule
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

Cholesterol is an essential molecule for your cells. Every cell’s membranes are
composed of about 30% cholesterol(1). Without this, cell’s membranes would be more
static, which would impair a multitude of cellular functions mediated through
membrane plasticity. Cholesterol has oil-like properties, meaning it doesn’t mix
well with water, which is the main ingredient in your blood. To circulate this
essential molecule in the bloodstream, it needs to be packaged, enters ApoB100.
This is a protein made by the liver to package cholesterol and other lipids. We
will then designate these ApoB100 with their lipid cargo as lipoproteins, and
stratify them on the proportion of lipid/ApoB100 in multiple classes which the
densest category (least amount of lipids/ApoB100) is the LDL particle (LDLp).
This is different then LDL cholesterol (LDLc) which refers to the total amount
of cholesterol molecules that were present in your LDL particles, and the
difference matters.





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-t-dayspring-t-dall-m-abuhajir--research-reports-clin-cardiol-2010&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/317442e508be53f644daa95867f56539.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;T Dayspring, T Dall, M Abuhajir - Research Reports Clin Cardiol, 2010&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/317442e508be53f644daa95867f56539.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    T Dayspring, T Dall, M Abuhajir - Research Reports Clin Cardiol, 2010
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that within what was classified long ago as LDLp, there is a range
of particle sizes. Their sizes have an impact on how likely you will be to build
plaque in your vessels, the smaller the particle, the more plaque
(atherosclerosis) you might build. So, while the LDLc may be associated with
plaque build-up at population levels, it is a crude metric that hides a stronger
signal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, we grew our understanding of the lipoprotein’s contribution to the
progression of atherosclerosis from LDLc to LDLp and now small LDLp. This
review; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.onlinejacc.org/content/76/7/844?fbclid=IwAR2KqXoyKyfoUJcqkUy-8RNj1XDLvLjKYwRNSivUaJO7bP-T_EyVxiKHY7c&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Saturated Fats and Health: A Reassessment and Proposal for Food-Based
Recommendations&lt;/a&gt;(2),
lead by one of the world’s lipoprotein experts Dr. Ronald Krauss, challenges the
current nutritional guidelines on the saturated fat intake that were founded on
our previous understanding of LDL’s role in atherosclerosis. Under the
presumption that either LDLc or all LDLp were important contributors to
atherosclerosis, a diet that showed an increase in either of these was (and
still is by most) considered dangerous and to be avoided. Their extensive review
makes the point that despite an increase in LDLc or overall LDLp in people that
have a diet high in saturated fat from dairy, dark chocolate, or unprocessed red
meat, in most cases, their all-cause mortality risk is reduced. This is not the
case of people who have an increase in small LDLp, which is strongly associated
with atherosclerosis progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-should-we-apply-this-to-our-lives&#34;&gt;How should we apply this to our lives?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, the take-home message is that saturated fats, as a group of
molecules, don’t seem to have a causal role in our risks of cardiovascular
diseases, and what matters is where these saturated fats came from (what food it
was packaged into). The consumption of &lt;strong&gt;unprocessed&lt;/strong&gt; foods high in saturated
fats is a healthy option for most (a subset of the population may not metabolize
these fats as efficiently and benefit from diets lower in saturated fats)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to dive deep in this subject, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterattiamd.com/ronkrauss/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is an interview with Dr. Krauss from my favorite podcast The Drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;BIBLIOGRAPHY&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang, J.; Li, Q.; Wu, Y.; Wang, D.; Xu, L.; Zhang, Y.; Wang, S.; Wang, T.;
Liu, F.; Zaky, M. Y., Cholesterol content in cell membrane maintains surface
levels of ErbB2 and confers a therapeutic vulnerability in ErbB2-positive breast
cancer. *Cell Communication and Signaling *&lt;strong&gt;2019,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;17&lt;/em&gt; (1), 1-12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astrup, A.; Magkos, F.; Bier, D. M.; Brenna, J. T.; de Oliveira Otto, M. C.;
Hill, J. O.; King, J. C.; Mente, A.; Ordovas, J. M.; Volek, J. S., Saturated
Fats and Health: A Reassessment and Proposal for Food-based Recommendations:
JACC State-of-the-Art Review. *Journal of the American College of Cardiology
*&lt;strong&gt;2020,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;76&lt;/em&gt; (7), 844-857.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
